<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Reason for the Propositions</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#per-acj1ac">Samuel Fynewver</name>
          <resp>Translator</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Reason for the Propositions</title>
          <date when="2025-04-16">April 16, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"
              >Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="E" n="en">Born Digital</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-16" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"> </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="la30px-aaa132">
        <head xml:id="la30px-aaa132-Hd1e103">Reason for the Propositions</head>
        <p xml:id="la30px-aaa132-d1e105"> 
          Reason for the Propositions
        </p>
        <p xml:id="la30px-aaa132-d1e114"> 
          Friar Bartolomé de las Casas or Casaus, Bishop of Chiapa
          in New Spain, knew—by virtue fifty years of personal experience—the spiritual needs which
          the Spanish have caused in these Indies. Those who lived in this diocese were bound by
          these spiritual needs, and they once were among those most in need of correction for their
          errors and sins. Given Las Casas’ pastoral office, providing a remedy for their dangerous
          blindness was his concern. Such a remedy is usually given, after preaching and doctrine,
          only through confession. For this reason, Las Casas wrote a brief Confessional
          (Confesionario), in which he assigned certain rules to guide the conscience of confessors.
          Having brought this Confessional to Castilla, it was read, reread and examined, and
          approved and signed by six masters of theology. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="la30px-aaa132-d1e158">
          But some who imitate the truth, ignorant of the true
          occurrences in the Indies, who would provide excuses for these most abominable happenings,
          wanted to defame the Confessional. They took issue with one of the rules in the
          Confessional, insisting that the Confessional would deny the kings of Castilla’s title and
          lordship over this world, since the Confessional affirms that everything the Spanish have
          done in the Indies is illegal, as a thing done without authority of a prince and against
          all natural justice. From this occasion the following propositions have their origin.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
