<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Prologue</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#per-acj1ac">Samuel Fynewver</name>
          <resp>Translator</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Prologue</title>
          <date when="2025-04-16">April 16, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"
              >Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="E" n="en">Born Digital</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-16" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"> </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="la30px-aaa158">
        <head xml:id="la30px-aaa158-Hd1e104">Prologue</head>
        <p xml:id="la30px-aaa158-d1e106"> 
          Prologue of the bishop friar Bartolomé de las Casas or
          Casaus to the very powerful and most Christian lords of the Royal Council of the Indies.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="la30px-aaa158-d1e119"> 
          Your Majesty sent me to call this Royal Council of the
          Indies about a Confessional I wrote which governs the confessors in hearing the
          confessions of the Spanish in my diocese. Some say that, from some of the rules in the
          Confessional, it could be inferred that the monarchs of Castilla have no title, or no good
          title, to the empire in the Indies. And it seemed to Your Majesty that I should declare in
          writing what I feel of this matter, for on various occasions in this Royal Council I have
          spoken in favor of my Confessional. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="la30px-aaa158-d1e148">
          This is a matter of great importance, and to give an
          account of it requires a long treatise, since it would need to come from expert men and
          excellent people. I have begun to collect what over the years I have thought and studied
          of it. However, since Your Majesty urges me to quickly send my position on the matter, it
          seemed best to do what I can, following the law of God, in a much abbreviated fashion.
          Therefore I write these Propositions, without proving them, in the current summary. Their
          proofs, with the rest, will be part of the said treatise4, which will be presented to Your
          Majesty in this Royal Council in brief days, should it please God. And because treating
          this subject necessarily requires discussing things concerning our holy faith, I submit
          everything I write herein to the correction of the Holy Roman Church. 
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
