<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Proposition 28</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#per-acj1ac">Samuel Fynewver</name>
          <resp>Translator</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Proposition 28</title>
          <date when="2025-04-16">April 16, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"
              >Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="E" n="en">Born Digital</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-16" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"> </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="la30px-bbb322">
        <head xml:id="la30px-bbb322-Hd1e104">Proposition 28</head>
        <p xml:id="la30px-bbb322-d1e106"> Proposition 28 </p>
        <p xml:id="la30px-bbb322-d1e111"> The encomienda and repartimiento are most evil. The
          devil could not invent any other pestilence to better destroy that entire world, consume
          and kill all the peoples therein and depopulate—as have been depopulated—such great and so
          populous kingdoms, than the repartimiento and encomiendas of these peoples. The Spaniards’
          encomiendas were established as if they were to hand these peoples over to all the devils,
          or like flocks of livestock handed over to hungry wolves. This encomienda or repartimiento
          is the most cruel tyranny and most worthy of hell fire that could be imagined. Because of
          it, all the peoples of the Americas are impeded from receiving the Christian faith. The
          Spaniards control their every day and night as unhappy tyrant comenderos, in the mines and
          personal work and incredible tributes, and by making them load great burdens on their
          backs to carry a hundred or two hundred leagues, as if and worse than if they were beasts.
          These comenderos also persecute and expel all the priests who preach the Gospel, who give
          them knowledge of God. All this is to say nothing of the violences, continuous larceny and
          homicide. Because of these encomiendas and repartimiento, the Indians have suffered and
          still suffer continuous torments, robberies, injustices in their persons and their
          children, women and goods. By these encomiendas and repartimientos, in the past forty-six
          years — I write as an eyewitness — more than fifteen million souls, without faith and without
          sacraments, have perished. They have also depopulated more than three thousand leagues of
          land, and I say this as an eyewitness. And as long as the encomiendas should endure — I pray
          that God be the judge of what I say — the monarchs’ power will not be enough, even if they
          were present in person, to stop the death, end, and consumption of all the Indians. By the
          encomienda, a thousand worlds would be destroyed, without having any remedy. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
